Guide to the Sensitive Skin Magazine Archive MSS.201
Fales Library and Special Collections
Sensitive Skin Magazine Archive
1991-1996
Fales Library and Special Collections
Sensitive Skin
Meisler, Bernard
MSS.201
1 Linear Feet in 1 record carton
Sensitive Skin magazine was a short-lived publication created and edited by Buddy Kold and Norman Douglas in 1991. The magazine published short fiction, poetry, screenwriting, reviews, essays, drawings, and photographs by established and emerging writers and artists, mostly from New York. The Sensitive Skin Magazine Archive consists of general documentation of the administrative activities of the magazine, as well as submissions and production files related to specific issues.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restricitions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Bernard Meisler in 2008. The accession number related to this gift is 2007.201.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged in alphabetical order by folder title. For the most part, original arrangement of material has been preserved. Much of the material arrived already grouped according to corresponding issue, and this arrangement has been maintained.
Historical Note
Sensitive Skin magazine was a short-lived publication created and edited by Buddy Kold and Norman Douglas in 1991. The first four issues were printed under the title "Peau Sensible" (French for "sensitive skin"), which had been translated to the English for subsequent issues. John Farris, Patricia Winter, and Darius James joined the editorial fold in 1992, while Mr. E. Oso took over editorial duties for the final issue in 1994. Kold remained the publisher throughout these years.
The magazine published short fiction, poetry, screenwriting, reviews, essays, drawings, and photographs by established and emerging writers and artists, mostly from New York. Sensitive Skin also frequently partnered with The Living Theatre to host release parties/ benefits where many of the published authors would read from their work and/or perform. St. Mark's Poetry Project and the Fez also hosted readings in conjunction with the magazine.
During its brief existence, Sensitive Skin published seminal downtown New York writers including John Giorno, Eileen Myles, David Rattray, Chris Kraus, David Ulin, Sparrow, Mike Topp, Ron Kolm, Richard Hell, Bob Holman, Wanda Phipps, Taylor Mead, among many others. Many of its published writers are part of the transgressive New York school, but a high degree of humour and wit also pervaded each issue. From haughty, pseudo-manifestoes to faux interviews, Sensitive Skin was careful not to take itself too seriously. Referring to the tongue-in-cheek subtitle of issue #2--"The magazine of art and literature that makes reading as fun and easy as watching TV!"--the editors, displaying this balance struck between the disturbing and the droll, write: "our magazine is not necessarily fun, or easy, to read. But for those who still search for interesting literature, and for the profound, the dark and the disturbing, Sensitive Skin is the place to look." (Box 1, Folder 5)
Scope and Contents
The Sensitive Skin Magazine Archive consists of general documentation of the administrative activities of the magazine from 1991 to 1995, as well as submissions and production files related to specific issues. Each issue folder may include correspondence, promotional material, original submissions (some annotated by editors), master copies, receipts, press, as well as other production documentation.
New York (N.Y.).; American fiction -- 20th century.; Magazines (Periodicals); Grant proposals.; Clippings (information artifacts); Manuscripts for publication.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Sensitive skin magazine; Meisler, Bernard; Sirowitz, Hal; Dawson, Fielding, 1930-2002; Giorno, John; Afflick, Lester, 1956-2000; Kolm, Ron; Sparrow, (American poet); Mead, Taylor; Sukenick, Ronald; Kern, Richard, 1954-; Hell, Richard; Rower, Ann, 1938-; Blagg, Max; Myles, Eileen; Holman, Bob, 1948-; Carter, Michael -- Correspondence
- Business-related documentation, circa 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  General
  Incl. business certificate, ISSN Application, resumes, and other related files
- Clippings, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence - Misc., circa 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Financial Documentation - Stores and Distribution, Advertising, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Grant Documentation, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Incl. Financial documentation; NYSCA (1985-86) and NEA (1988-89) applications for Ikon Press
- Issues #1-5, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Issue #5 - signed by contributors, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Mailing Lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- MIscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Peau Sensible #1 (Nov./Dec. 1991) - submissions, receipts, master copy (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Peau Sensible #2 (Winter 1992) - submissions (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Peau Sensible #3 (Spring 1992) - submissions, correspondence, master copy (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Peau Sensible #3 (Spring 1992) - submissions, correspondence, clippings (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Peau Sensible #4 (Summer 1992) - submissions, receipts, master copy (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Peau Sensible #4 (Summer 1992) - artwork submissions (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Peau Sensible #4 (Summer 1992) - rejected submissions (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Promotional - Readings/Event Announcements, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Sensitive Skin #5 (Summer/Fall 1993) - submissions, correspondence (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Sensitive Skin #2 (Spring/Summer 1994) - submissions, correspondence, master copy (Box 1, Folder 19)
  [original folder titled "Sensitive Skin #6]
- Submissions - Alternates A, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Submissions - Alternates A, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Submissions - Alternates B, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Submissions - "maybes", undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Submissions - misc., undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Submissions - rejected artwork, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Submissions - to be read, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Submissions - to be read, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 27)